Finding Aid for Ted Heusel Papers, 1968-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ted Heusel Papers 1968-1974
Heusel, Ted
85204 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, radio personality and member of the Ann Arbor (Mich.) Board of Education, 1968-1973. Materials relating to his service on the school board; subjects covered include disruptions in the schools, teacher strikes, alleged racial and sexual bias in the school system, and the searches for school superintendents.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
4 linear feet
The collection was received from Mr. Heusel (donor no. 6964 ) in August 1983.
The collection is open to research.
Theodore (Ted) Heusel, news director for radio station WPAG in Ann Arbor, served two terms on the Board of Education for the Ann Arbor Public Schools. He was elected to his first three-year term in June 1968, and was re-elected in June 1971. During 1971-1972 he served as vice-president of the Board, and as President during 1972-1973. The years of Heusel's tenure, 1968-1974, were eventful ones as the Board confronted such diverse issues as student disruptions, teacher strikes, problems relating to racial and sexual discrimination, the Board's adoption of a discipline policy, and the selection of two superintendents.
The papers of Ted Heusel relate to his tenure on the Ann Arbor Board of Education. While the dates of the collection are 1968-1974, the bulk of the material is from 1972-1973. The collection has been arranged into six series: Correspondence, Memoranda, Minutes and Notes, Topical Files, Reports, and Sound Recordings.
The Correspondence and Memoranda series consist basically of communications between board members and school administrators, but including also some communications with teachers and parents. These files are in chronological order.
Minutes and Notes have been arranged chronologically by type of meeting: briefing session, executive session, or regular meeting. There are no minutes and notes for 1971.
Topical Files are in alphabetical order. Included in these files are clippings, minutes and recommendations of various committees, curriculum guides data sheets, and surveys. many of the concerns of the Board at this time, such as discipline policy, a humaneness in education policy, multi-ethnic curriculum, and the formulation of goals and objectives for the school system, are documented in this series of the collection.
The Reports relate to both the educational program and to physical facilities of the Ann Arbor Public Schools.
The Sound Recordings were prepared in the early 1970's in conjunction with Heusel's radio program, and are not directly related to the Board of Education. They do, however, include the opinions of listeners who called in to express their views during the teachers' strike as well as news, interviews, and comments on other local events and personalities.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.). Board of Education.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Public schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Correspondence
  - 1968-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - January-September (Box 1)
    - October-December (Box 1)
  - 1973
    - January-February (Box 1)
    - March-April (Box 1)
    - May (Box 1)
    - June-December (Box 1)
- Memoranda
  - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - 1972
    - March-August (Box 1)
    - September (Box 1)
    - October 5-October 16 (Box 1)
    - October 18-October 31 (Box 1)
    - November (Box 1)
    - December (Box 1)
  - 1973
    - January (Box 1)
    - February 1-February 8 (Box 1)
    - February 12-February 28 (Box 1)
    - March 1-March 15 (Box 1)
    - March 16-March 31 (Box 1)
    - April 1-April 10 (Box 2)
    - April 11-April 30 (Box 2)
    - May 1-May 13 (Box 2)
    - May 14-May 30 (Box 2)
    - June 1-June 8 (Box 2)
    - June 11-June 27 (Box 2)
    - July-November (Box 2)
  - 1974 (Box 2)
- Minutes and Notes
  - Briefing Sessions
    - 1970 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
  - Executive Sessions 1970, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Regular Meetings
    - 1968 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973
      - January-July (Box 2)
      - October-December (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
- Topical Files
  - Athletics and Physical Education 1972, 1983, undated (Box 2)
  - Board Policies and Procedures, Bylaws, Code of Ethics 1967-1968, 1973, undated (Box 2)
  - Capital Planning (Advanced Planning Research Group) 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Career Education 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1968, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Committees
    - Advisory Committee on Michigan High School Athletics Association 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Advisory Committee on Special Educational Needs 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Public Library Advisory Committee 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Central Finance Committee 1973 (Box 2)
    - New Construction Coordinating Committee 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Slauson New Addition Committee 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Special Category Schools Committee 1972 (Box 2)
    - Contract Negotiations 1967-1968, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Curriculum (Box 3)
    - Ann Arbor High School Curriculum Guide 1966 (Box 3)
    - Environmental Education Program 1971, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Multi-ethnic 1973, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Music 1971-1972 (Box 3)
  - Data Sheets
    - Enrollment, Staff, Census 1956-1957, 1960, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Assessment Program 1970 (Box 3)
  - Discipline Policy 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Elections
    - Millage and Bond Proposal 1968, 1973 (Box 3)
    - School Board Candidates 1968, 1973, undated (Box 3)
  - Evaluations
    - Community High School 1973 (Box 3)
    - Middle School 1973 (Box 3)
    - Title I Preschool Program 1970 (Box 3)
  - Financial Reports
    - Annual Financial Report 1972, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Budget and Data 1967-1968, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Goals and Objectives for School System 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Handbooks
    - Handbook for Teachers in the Elementary Schools 1962 (Box 3)
    - IRMA (Information, Resources, Materials, Assistance) 1971 (Box 3)
    - Pioneer High School Student Handbook 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Human Relations Ombudsman 1971-1973 (Box 3)
  - Humaneness in Education
    - Elementary Schools 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Junior and Senior High Schools 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea 1970, 1972-1973, undated (Box 3)
  - News Releases 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - P.T.O. Council 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Resolutions 1972, undated (Box 3)
  - Search for Superintendent 1973 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  - Small House (Slauson and Forsythe Schools) 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Student Advocate School Board 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - Surveys of Public Opinion
    - Attitudes of Ann Arbor Voters Toward Their Public Schools 1971 (Box 3)
    - Attitudes Toward the Split-Trimester Extended School Year 1971 (Box 3)
    - What are the School Board Voters Really Talking About? 1974 (Box 3)
  - Washtenaw Intermediate School District 1969, 1972 (Box 3)
- Reports, Bound Volumes
  - Ann Arbor Growth Study (Impact on Schools) (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor Schools Survey 1974
    - Volume I, History and Curriculum Review (Box 4)
    - Part III, Growth and Enrollments Report (Box 4)
    - Part V, Review of School Buildings (Box 4)
  - Appraisal Report 1972 (Box 4)
  - Board of Education Policies and Administrative Regulations (adopted 1968-1970) (Box 4)
  - Budget for 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Educational Plan and Architectural Services 1971 (Box 4)
  - Logan (Slauson) Middle School Summary Report 1972 (Box 4)
  - Master Plan for Education 1973
    - Volume II, Physical Plan (Box 4)
    - Volume III, Education Plan (Box 4)
  - Physical Facilities Inventory System 1972 (Box 4)
  - Student-School Attendance Area 1974-1975, 2 volumes (Box 4)
- Sound recordings, 7 inch reel; 7-1/2 ips
  - Actualities
    - February 18-March 11, 1970 Various topics (list of contents in box) (Box 4)
    - March 11-March 17, 1970 various topics (list of contents in box) (Box 4)
    - May 9-August 18, 1970 Various topics (list of contents in box) (Box 4)
  - Community Comment (undated)
    - Teachers' Strike (Box 4)
    - Various Topics (list of contents in box) (Box 4)
  - Hank Bryant (Model Cities) August 25, 1971 (Box 4)